[Avoid “taking a Part for the Whole"]
Confusing elephants with fleas
will lead to an unconvincing conclusion.
There are also Chinese who think that
online shopping and express delivery
are on the basis of
exploiting the delivery man.
Can China's current system avoid
social unrest caused by the polarization
between the rich and the poor?
How does the China Model blend
various new interest groups
into the existing political system?
China Now with Zhang Weiwei
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
China is so large.
Whether from this angle
or another.
It is easy to be like "the blind men and an elephant".
[making biased judgment]
Someone is viewing through a telescope
while others through spherical lenses.
The picture is either changing size
or getting twisted.
He did not see through his own eyes.
Because he has not practically
come to China.
I read a quote the other day.
I think it makes sense.
China is so large.
What you think everyone knows,
might be unknown to 1.3 billion people.
Yes (laughs)
I think it’s a vivid metaphor.
Not only the ordinary Chinese,
but many intellectuals in China
have no idea about China at all.
For instance, they worry about “middle-income trap”
and “Thucydides Trap” [tendency towards war between
emerging power and hegemon]
All the examples and models are from abroad.
The key is whether one is willing to
think of China as a country with unbalanced development
and complicated national conditions.
China's economy has developed rapidly over the years,
with per capita income also rising,
but China is still a developing country.
This conclusion
is in conflict with their starting point
—they don't think China is a developing country.
It’s all about the mindset.
When facing the unknown,
you either want to know more about it
or rely on your preconceived notions.
Put a label on it first.
And then apply it with the known.
For example, the thing I touched seemed to be a bump.
Then I said that's the nose.
In fact, it might be an ear instead.
But the problem is that some people
just close their eyes and do not want to see.
Then whether they are willing to
discuss this problem with us.
In fact, I think it is necessary to communicate patiently.
There is an easy way.
Just open up tourism.
Let them first visit China themselves.
Then they will see.
There is a joke that
an Indian friend says
Indians can eat anything by hand.
Then how about hot pot?
Although just being humorous and a little bit cruel,
it really works.
In fact, let's rethink this more carefully.
Forty years ago, before the reform and opening up,
did we make an overall judgment of the world
like "the blind men feeling the elephant"?
Yes, we also might have been subjective.
So we are going through that process.
We are gradually becoming more and more
open and confident.
And our judgment of the world
is getting closer to reality.
I do think that
the more important point
lies in the self-awareness of Chinese
people being incomplete.
I think a lot of anxiety comes from
the incomplete understanding of oneself.
Not knowing enough about ourselves.
Even in the past few decades
We opened our eyes
to look at the world very carefully.
But we haven't studied ourselves very well.
I think if we're like “the blind men feeling the elephant”,
this is a part of the elephant that we must be clear about.
I talked to the audience just now.
They collected a lot of questions.
Sharp ones?
Exactly.
They would ask Prof. Zhang directly,
when will China be reunified?
And the timing of the reunification
— will it be more beneficial to China's national
rejuvenation to reunify sooner or later?
Quite straightforward.
In the 19th National Congress Report
by President Xi Jinping [2017],
the timing for national rejuvenation
is clearly written.
Actually, about “Taking a Part for the Whole”,
Taiwan is the most typical example.
They were talking about tea flavored boiled eggs.
Yeah, and that isn’t a joke.
I feel that the more media freedom they claim to have,
the more ignorant they are.
The United States is also a typical example.
The Americans cannot even figure out
the location of Beijing and North Korea.
Yeah.
All right, it’s time for the speech.
Sure.
Different views can be discussed and debated.
We are not afraid of competition.
China, be confident.
China Now with Zhang Weiwei
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Hello everyone,
welcome to China Now.
We are here to learn about China,
comprehend China, position China,
and understand China.
Standing next to me
is our keynote speaker,
Prof. Zhang Weiwei, Director of
the China Institute of Fudan University.
Welcome!
Here, Prof. Zhang
will give a keynote speech.
Meanwhile, our audience will have the
chance to talk with Prof. Zhang.
And also, our pre-production panel
will ask their questions
I am looking forward to the brainstorming.
Now, I will give the stage
to Prof. Zhang.
Welcome!
It’s not easy to comprehend China.
Because China is too large.
I always say that China is a mega-country.
If measured by the size of its population,
China roughly equals to
a hundred European countries combined.
You can take a look at
the average population of a country in Europe.
It's about 14 million,
while China is near 1.4 billion.
Therefore, when understanding China one often
encounters a problem called
“blind men and an elephant”.
Everyone only touches one part of an elephant.
When you touch the ears,
you describe it as a big fan
When you touch the nose,
you say it’s like a round cylinder.
Then how exactly
can we understand China?
Firstly, there's the issue about "per capita".
For instance，
the weather forecast today says that
the average temperature in Singapore is 35 degrees.
It is generally known that Singapore is small.
I have checked that the size of Singapore
is about a twenty-third of Beijing,
and one-ninth of Shanghai.
So the 35 degrees in a weather forecast
must be quite accurate.
But if you say the average temperature today is 35
degrees in the People’s Republic of China,
no one can actually make sense of it.
Because this country is too large.
When the northeast is frozen in snow,
Hainan is still hot.
Another issue is the housing price.
Everyone says that house prices are high.
But suddenly someone argues that
houses aren’t expensive.
In their town, the average price last year was RMB 7000
or 8,000 per square meter. [about US$100 per sq feet]
So I think, to understand China,
we need add innovation into the indicator system.
In sports competition,
we have to classify different kinds of
champions and runner-ups.
For instance, heavyweight and lightweight players
are separated in boxing.
Actually, country-to-country competitions
are far more complicated than boxing.
Therefore, when you just use some simple data,
it’s hard to draw a conclusion.
I often mention that
even the calculation of GDP has
two different standards.
One is according to the official exchange rate of the US dollar,
and the other is called
calculation of purchasing power parity (PPP).
We know that the PPP calculation
looks at how many things the
currency can actually buy
and nominally compare to how it exceeds the
exchange rate of the official US dollar.
Personally, I have always believed that
PPP is more accurate
I have traveled to more than a hundred countries.
and relatively speaking,
I think PPP is more reliable.
But some scholars think that it's better
to use the official exchange rate.
But it’s all right.
Both of them are simply one of the ways to get to the truth.
Our economic aggregate is very large,
but per capita GDP is still lagging behind.
This kind of interpretation actually faces some challenges.
One is from our social indicators.
Actually, it’s good on the whole.
For example,
China’s level of median household net worth,
especially in our developed cities,
has surpassed the United States.
This is comparable to the United States and Europe.
We do not lag behind.
It shows that Chinese people are living in wealth.
There is a chart. You can take a look.
This blue curve
represents the median level of the
family net assets of the American middle-class.
The gray curve below shows
the changes of median net assets
in all American households.
The two both peaked in 2007.
Then just fell with the emergence of the
2008 financial crisis.
By 2013,
the median net assets in a
middle-class American family
was $122,000.
Then the median net assets of American households
should be even lower,
which was $72,000.
If we take $122,000 as a cap, and $72,000 a lower limit.
Converted to RMB,
that is about 500,000 yuan and 850,000 yuan.
These are including real estates.
Based on common sense, I think everyone
probably knows China's current level [of net assets].
Actually, all this data is open to the public,
but many of our scholars are afraid to use it.
They can’t believe that Chinese people
should be richer than Americans.
If you have lived in the US,
you will know it’s a consensus that
many Chinese live better than Americans.
There is another social indicator,
which I deem important.
The average life expectancy.
I have another chart.
You can look at the dark blue areas.
Beijing, Tianjin, Shanghai, and Zhejiang
have the average life expectancy around 80.
It has already exceeded America which is 79.
When adding up the population of these four regions
— Beijing, Tianjin, Shanghai, Zhejiang
The population is 150 million.
The blue area below
indicates the life expectancy 77 to 80 years old,
which is still comparable to 79-year-old
in the United States.
The population in the dark blue and the blue areas altogether
is over 500 million.
That is to say, more than 500 million people’s life expectancy in China
is actually very close to that in America,
or even higher.
And another important social indicator,
is public security.
China’s public security is recognized as one of the
best in the world.
This chart here.
You can take a look.
Crime involving death per 100 thousand population in China [0.62],
is one of the lowest in the world.
And much lower than the United States [5.53].
When it comes to
economic and social progress,
there is a more comprehensive indicator.
Just ask the people:
are you satisfied with the current situation
in your country?
With the economic status?
Or ask in another way:
are you satisfied with your country's
path of development?
These are all very subjective.
But it is very telling.
Look at the chart here.
The latest polls at the Pew Center
reveals that the dissatisfaction rate with
the economic situation in China is 11%;
while in some countries like France and Greece,
the rate is over 80% and 90%.
By giving these examples,
I want to probe towards the following question:
Why is China's GDP per capita not very high,
according to the official exchange rate statistics,
but our social indicators and the overall
degree of satisfaction of the people
are still relatively high
in an international comparison.
I have several explanations,
and one of which verifies
the superiority of our political system.
I always like to compare New York with Shanghai.
Because these two cities are both familiar to me.
According to the official exchange rate,
New York's GDP per capita is at least
four times higher than Shanghai’s.
But when it comes to some key social indicators,
like the median household net worth,
life expectancy per capita, public security,
or the polls indicating whether most of the residents
are optimistic about the future of the city,
Shanghai is significantly better than New York.
You can also see that
the cars on the street in Shanghai
are actually better than that in New York.
Meanwhile, Shanghai’s residents also use
better mobile phones,
as well as household appliances and so on.
So I think,
we can draw such a conclusion:
although our GDP per capita
is only a quarter or even less [than America’s],
our political system,
the socialist system with Chinese characteristics,
is quite successful, at least in Shanghai,
or the developed areas in China.
China did what the United States could not do.
There is another interpretation,
which I also deem important.
Besides our obvious advantages in the political system,
there are some problems with the
method of calculating GDP.
At least we use different methods from America's.
There is a lot of economic activity
in our rural areas that is not counted.
I always said that during our reform and opening up in the past 40 years,
farmers' mud houses all turned into brick houses,
tile-roofed houses, or multi-storey buildings.
If you go to the countryside,
you’ll see some of the people are still "planting houses",
in order to get more compensation
for land requisition in the future.
Many of these activities are not actually counted.
In the city,
you can notice that there are many street vendors.
This is a big industrial chain.
But these are not actually counted either.
We call it "giving the fish more water than they need".
Sometimes the city management officers will interfere.
But this kind of business activity is counted abroad.
For example, in Italy, even drug trafficking and prostitution,
these kinds of informal business, are also counted.
So I think overall,
our statistical method,
due to many reasons,
results in underestimating our own GDP.
This is just my personal opinion.
Sometimes, I also think about
a more fundamental question:
how to jump out from the Western indicator system?
Many western indicators are from their social practice,
or from their own theories.
Therefore, when these indicators are
applied in other countries, like China,
it would often result in misreading [the situation].
Take the "Gini coefficient" as an example.
[a statistical measure of income inequality]
Can the Gini coefficient accurately interpret China?
We know the scale value of the Gini coefficient
is between 0 and 1.
Normally, 0.4 is regarded as a warning line of the gap
between the rich and the poor.
Once the value is greater than 0.4,
it’s likely to cause social unrest.
Many people think that the Gini coefficient
in China is over 0.47.
But if you look at the definition of the Gini coefficient,
it actually calculates
the monetized income.
Is it accurate or not to talk about China
with respect to "monetized income"?
Because in fact, we are socialist countries.
After the land reform,
farmers own land and houses.
But none of these are counted.
Otherwise, I’m afraid it won't be the same.
Moreover, China is a very large country.
When comparing the richest places in Shanghai
with the poorest ones in Tibet,
the Gini coefficient must be the highest in the world.
Can the Gini coefficient actually adjust to
the measurement of such a large country?
Meanwhile, even if we look at a smaller region,
for example, researching the Gini coefficient in Shanghai City,
or Jiangsu Province,
you can find that overall,
it is still within a relatively reasonable range.
It reveals a problem: how should a
large-scaled countries be measured?
Is the Gini coefficient [in this case] suitable?
I think this should be questioned.
There is also another indicator:
the number of outbound travelers,
which Western countries often use.
According to official statistics,
the number of China’s outbound
travelers in 2017 was 130 million,
already ranking highest in the world.
But in fact, I think this figure is still a bit conservative.
Because I lived in Europe for a long time,
European countries are quite small.
Traveling from Beijing to Shanghai will take
one hour and forty to fifty minutes by plane.
The distance traveled can at least
cover ten European countries, right?
Therefore, in China, strictly speaking,
In terms of economic capacity,
anyone who can afford taking a plane
or a high-speed train
all have the ability to go abroad,
especially based on European standards.
Another concept we often hear is
the “middle income trap”,
which was defined by the World Bank.
I never use it.
The World Bank report released that,
13 countries or economies have successfully
crossed the “middle income trap”.
When I checked which countries are included,
I found that even Equatorial Guinea,
and Mauritius were included.
I said to myself, this would cause trouble.
Ten years ago, per capita GDP of Equatorial Guinea
surpassed Beijing and Shanghai
reaching US$ 20,000.
But, from my experience in Africa,
at least 15 years ago, in Equatorial Guinea,
half of the residents did not even have running water.
Because of oil exploration,
some foreign companies came and invested.
Then the GDP per capita soared at once.
It has nothing to do with surpassing
the middle income trap.
I find it very confusing.
Same with Mauritius.
It's quite a small country,
equivalent to just one county in China.
Only relying on tourism,
its GDP could rise up.
But once encountering a crisis,
it’s GDP will decline rapidly.
So I think country-to-country comparisons
should be differentiated by scales.
Otherwise, I'm afraid it’s going
away from understanding China.
Comparing these small countries to China
is kind of like putting elephants and fleas together,
then ending up at an unconvincing conclusion.
Small countries have their strengths
and limitations as well.
I have a good friend from Singapore,
and he said that their current
GDP per capita is quite high,
but they feel like walking on thin ice.
If an event like "9/11" happened,
Singapore would be broken.
This is really the case.
This is unlike China. We have the ability to
withstand all kinds of disasters.
Even undergoing a catastrophe
like the Wenchuan earthquake,
the national economy still remained the same.
That's due to their different scales.
China’s advantage, as a large country,
lies in having enough room for maneuver.
Comparing elephants with fleas
will lead to incorrect conclusions.
I think we have to "seek truth from facts".
I study politics.
Actually, in politics and other social sciences,
Western mainstream scholars have made many efforts.
But for various reasons,
they still cannot fully understand China.
Take politics as an example,
political scholars' predictions
about China are almost always wrong.
Western mainstream scholars not only
failed to predict China’s development,
but even the collapse of the Soviet Union.
Neither the rise of China nor
Trump's presidency were predicated.
Western mainstream economists almost all
failed to predict the 2008 financial crisis.
Western so-called social sciences are all trying to
apply natural science methods
and various mathematical models.
But now [western societies] seem
unable to cope with the challenges
brought by the diversity and complexity
in human society.
Can't deal with it.
So I always say that Chinese scholars,
and even our entire academy,
should end the era of “working” for Western discourse.
This era should be ended.
The so-called "breaking" comes first,
then the "making" follows.
Deconstruct Western discourse
and construct Chinese discourse.
So should we comprehend China?
I want to share some of my experiences.
I mainly use three methods.
Firstly, I pay more attention to big data and big polls,
especially released by authoritative organizations.
And you need to compare them against each other.
For example, if you review the data from Pew Center,
Ipsos and Asian Barometer,
their predictions about China as a whole:
Are you satisfied with the development situation
or the development path of your nation?
They have been asking these questions
for three years, five years and ten years.
Probably you can draw a more cautious
conclusion by comparing comprehensively.
Secondly, I advocate fieldwork and research.
You should have a look there.
And you will have a clearer mind.
You can't make publications in the ivory tower.
Just reading data in your study
will end up with a strikingly wrong conclusion.
Thirdly, to comprehend China,
because of its large scale,
I think we need to interpret by sectors.
I often call one sector the "developed sector",
and the other "emerging economy sector".
Then we look at the interaction
between these two sectors.
You have to observe dynamically
instead of statically.
I think it will be easier to understand China
by merging these methods.
In short, understanding China requires
the spirits and methods of "seeking truth from facts".
Some issues need to be studied in advance.
What stage is China at now?
What improvements should be made
to the indicator system?
Especially now, under the Belt and Road Initiative,
China opens to the world with such a large scale.
We learn more about developing countries,
such as Africa, Latin America,
and also know more about the West, in order
to accurately comprehend the current situation.
Then we can generate our strategic focus
which I deem the most important.
All right, that’s all for today. Thank you all.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
The applause was to Prof. Zhang.
Thank you. Please have a seat.
Through speech, Prof. Zhang told us
how to observe China.
Actually, I have a question.
Prof. Zhang, you particularly emphasize
observing China at current,
and avoid taking a part for the whole.
The adverbial “at current” reveals a sense of urgency.
Then conversely,
what if we still use some of the previous standards
or some Western systems to observe China?
For us Chinese, we must fully understand China first.
This is very important.
The positioning of our Central
Committee is accurate:
"from standing up, to getting rich, and to getting strong".
This is a great leap.
I think it’s quite accurate.
Then I think it's the same for foreign countries.
How should we present the real China? The answer
is through confident and equal communication.
It’s very important right now.
Because we are on the threshold.
Prof. Zhang also said,
what we should do now is "breaking",
and then next is “making”.
So there is much room for us to
discuss and communicate.
Our pre-production panel have already grabbed
the microphone and are ready to ask questions.
When doing pre-production editing,
I collected some information
and also some sharp questions.
For example, some Chinese think that China’s
online shopping express delivery is very wasteful
and is based on capitalists exploiting
the delivery man.
What’s your opinion, Prof. Zhang?
This person must "keep up with the times".
In fact, the appearance of the delivery man is
an interesting phenomenon in China now.
What I can see is that through their own hard work,
they provide a very good service.
In addition, they also earn respect.
President Xi specially praised the couriers
in his speech on New Year’s Day.
And also sent greetings to them.
It's a new phenomenon in China.
I also heard that the overall salary is quite good.
So I think, this is in accordance with Marxism.
It’s nothing to do with exploitation,
but "more pay for more work".
I think this is in line with Socialism
with Chinese Characteristics
and the theory of the primary stage of socialism.
So the person who asks this question
must keep up with the times.
They also get Five Insurances and One Housing Fund.
Right.
I feel that many statistical methods
and concepts in the West
are put forward for countries with a
population of one million to ten million.
In mathematics,
some people may take it for granted that
the population increases linearly,
so you can deal with other situations
by just adding the multiples.
But I always have a doubt that
when it comes to countries
with populations of hundreds of millions
like America or countries with
billion populations like China and India,
should we abandon this method?
We can't add a simple weight
according to the population growth multiple.
Instead, it may be like a moving object
that exceeds the speed of light,
which will go beyond the knowledge of
the original system.
Do you think this will really happen?
This is a qualitative change.
When a country like China reaches such a scale,
if you still do a comparison between
the "elephant" and the "flea",
it will be like comparing a glass with an apple.
Of course, you can say that they are
all comprised of molecules and atoms.
But this kind of comparison is almost meaningless.
You should compare their similar types.
As I mentioned earlier, in a conversation with
a journalist from the New York Times,
I used this example.
I said if I set up a cram school [test-prep school],
it will be a school of only fifty or sixty students.
But if I run a university like Fudan,
which has 30,000 students.
Then the management method
will be completely different, right?
The same can be applied to national governance.
There is a big difference.
This question is really interesting.
Sometimes these indicators and data
are totally different from how we perceive in our life.
This means that whether
our own perception goes wrong,
or there is a problem with the indicator system itself.
How to quantify such factors as peace,
stability and security?
In different environments, such as
in peaceful or disorderly environments,
the same things may have different valuations.
The old saying that
"in the age of prosperity, antiques are preserved;
while in troubled times, gold is preferred."
Antiques and gold are unchanged.
However, antiques cannot even
trade a steamed bread in warring times.
But the valuation of many of our assets today
such as land, houses and antiques,
in a sense,
are the appreciation of security, peace and stability.
Right. The so-called new
research methods of social science
applied by the West also face such a dilemma.
Just for the sake of mathematical establishment,
they have to define some variables and factors.
It will be completely different,
if you remove or add variables.
I particularly agree with what
Mr. Hong Lin just said.
Some of our Chinese sayings are
taken for granted and regarded as cliché.
You can tell them to the West:
This is our wisdom.
We have been talking about peace and development for decades.
Indeed, we have just said that
through a period of practice,
we gradually realize that some Western standards,
systems or some of their concepts
are unable to solve and interpret China’s situation.
The problem is by which standards
can we observe China properly,
and how we can build our own systems.
I believe Prof. Zhang gave us a lot of inspiration.
We can all start thinking.
Let's communicate further and inspire each other.
So next I will invite some in the audience
to ask questions.
Please raise your hands.
Yes, the girl in white, please.
Prof. Zhang, I have seen the debate between
you and Huntington’s student Fukuyama.
I think Huntington affirmed the Chinese Communist
Party’s ability to establish political order.
Since the reform and opening up,
China’s development was largely attributed to
our stable political order over the past four decades.
But during the 40 years of reform and opening up,
many emerging interest groups sprung up.
They may have different interest demands,
and they should be more involved in the political system.
How does the China Model blend
various emerging interest groups
into the existing political system,
and make their voices heard?
China Now with Zhang Weiwei
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Can China's current system avoid social unrest caused
by the polarization between the rich and the poor?
Can we avoid following the rule of history
that great powers rise and decline?
All economies, when reaching a certain level,
will have a few people at the top seizing wealth quickly,
but the rest of the people will be lagging behind.
When talking about the gap between rich and poor,
many people get excited immediately.
How could China make such great progress
when facing so many problems?
China Now with Zhang Weiwei
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
How does the China Model blend
various emerging interest groups
into the existing political system?
and make their voices heard?
Thank you.
A very profound observation!
Can I ask if you are a student?
Yes, I am.
What do you study?
I study social work.
Ah, social work.
She studies Huntington and also pays attention
to Fukuyama's point of view.
Awesome. Please have a seat.
Great question.
In my opinion,
if you observe closely,
you will find the theory of "Three Represents"
proposed by Jiang Zemin
is largely in order to solve this problem.
"Representing the fundamental interests of the
masses" is one of the "Three Represents".
Meanwhile, China’s Communist Party
is open to emerging social classes,
I don’t know when Jack Ma joined the Party.
But anyway, Jack Ma is also a Party member.
There is a sector called "new social class" in the
Chinese People's Political Consultative Conference [CPPCC].
Right, Jack Ma actually represents a new social class.
How does China integrate them
into the current political system,
or what we call the "socialist consultative democracy"?
The first step is to make them
a part of the consultative democracy,
typically the CPPCC itself,
and the People's Congress.
Besides, one good tradition in our Party is
“of the people, for the people”.
There is an example.
Didi [ride-hailing] is now legal in China,
but illegal in Germany.
Because Uber impacted the existing taxi industry
after coming to Germany.
Then the typical approach in the West is to litigate.
As a legal society, if you have lived in the West,
you will know that it benefits those with vested interests.
So generally speaking, the taxi driver
is much more likely to win.
Thus Uber was banned.
France is a similar case.
But Uber is legalized in China.
You see, although there are many questions,
we can solve the emerging ones
in the developing process.
An important condition is that
we have such a mechanism for consultative democracy.
Didi may have no representatives in the CPPCC,
the National People ’s Congress or
the Central Committee of the CCP.
But it doesn't matter.
Once it reflects new social needs or interests,
the Communist Party will take it into consideration.
The public opinion can be heard
through some special ways,
for instance, a CPPCC proposal,
an article on the Internet or
a research on a heated topic.
Then Didi will be invited to the city government
to talk about their demands.
Then some research will be conducted again.
After a few rounds,
we will find a solution that can be accepted
by the traditional taxi industry, Didi
and the general public.
I give this example to illustrate that
our system does have ways to
deal with these problems.
Through your questions, I can really feel that
everyone is thinking deeply.
Next let us continue to hear more thoughts.
Alright, our friend over here.
Good evening,
may I ask that
since you have studied the China Path
and the current system,
can China's current system avoid social unrest caused
by the polarization between the rich and the poor?
Then avoid following the rule of history
that great powers rise and decline?
Thank you.
Do you like to read or study history?
Yes, I do.
What line of work are you in?
Automotive paint testing.
So you see, no matter what occupation you are in,
as long as you have interest in
studying China’s development,
you can find your own perspective.
It's awesome. Please have a seat.
Thank you.
In fact, your analysis makes sense.
We really need to pay attention to
the gap between the rich and the poor.
But at the same time,
China has basically found the solution,
although it still needs improvement.
I always say that,
first of all, our indicator system should be innovative.
We cannot simply apply the Gini coefficient
as mentioned before.
There must be a new indicator system.
If you look at it from another angle,
you’ll see this is basically China’s pathway of development:
At the beginning of reform and opening up,
Deng Xiaoping put forward a complete concept:
First, let some regions get rich,
then promote prosperity in other regions;
Second, let some people get rich first,
then mobilize more people
to achieve common prosperity.
That’s the full statement.
If you look at the first step,
"Let some regions get rich first,
then promote prosperity in other regions".
We have basically achieved that.
In the past 20 years,
Central and western China
are developing faster than the coastal areas,
and you can really feel it.
This has actually facilitated the
poverty alleviation of the local areas.
By 2020, we will overcome all
poverty under current standards.
This is amazing.
I personally think it is a miracle in human history.
In China, 740 million people have been
lifted out of poverty now.
So in this aspect, much progress has been made.
However, the second part
"let some people get rich first,
then mobilize more people to
achieve common prosperity"
— this is still being explored.
How can we achieve this more effectively?
Although we have had several trials,
it has not yet reached its optimal state.
Fortunately, our goal is very clear.
That is to achieve common prosperity.
And we are advancing in this direction.
When it comes to the gap between rich and poor,
many people will get excited immediately.
You must observe the bigger picture,
instead of thinking in a simple and radical way.
Generally speaking, China is advancing
towards common prosperity,
and many people have been living a better life.
Nowhere else in the world can you
find this kind of transformation.
Meanwhile, the prospect is still promising.
So I think we should think outside the box.
The vicious cycle [rise and decline]
as you mentioned can be averted.
China is still focusing
on targeted poverty alleviation.
This is also one of our special practices.
Prof. Zhang, as you have traveled so many countries,
is there any place that alleviates poverty in this way?
Targeted poverty alleviation actually
has particular requirements.
First of all, the scale of poverty-stricken
population should be relatively small,
No targeted poverty alleviation can be conducted
with 700 million impoverished people.
Secondly, the government must
have a relatively strong capability
to be able to reach the grass roots.
Most developing countries have
not yet reached this stage.
As long as you have conducted field trips,
you will find that
the central government of a typical developing country
may only be able to manage the capital city.
But even farmers from the poorest
places in Guizhou have bank accounts.
Our government can remit money
to them through their bank cards.
This is an important symbol of modern
management: digital management.
So to propose targeted poverty alleviation,
and perform the duties are actually quite tough.
Only after developing to a certain level
can the government have the ability to do so.
Forty years of reform and opening-up
lifted 740 million people out of poverty.
What we need to do next is to targeted poverty alleviation.
So actually these two points combined
were trying to answer your concerns.
We all have this kind of concern.
And we also hope the common prosperity
can be achieved sooner.
I want to ask Prof. Zhang,
Will all economies,
after developing to a certain level,
inevitably allow the people at the top to seize wealth quickly,
leaving most people behind?
Is this unsolvable?
If you look at the facts,
China has grown at an average
annual rate of 9.5% over the past 40 years.
With such a growth rate,
it will necessarily generate a large number
of rich people and entrepreneurs every year.
Otherwise, it is impossible to
push economic development.
I have an observation about
the gap between rich and poor.
Let me share with you a story that touches me.
A story about a young entrepreneur under forty,
with assets worthy of hundreds of millions yuan.
Recently, many people were saying
China’s taxes on SMEs are getting heavier.
Many businesspeople cannot survive,
so they choose to invest abroad.
The young entrepreneur said privately, not on the forum:
the wealth we have accumulated over the years
are the dividends from the policy.
We should not forget the policy:
let some people get rich first,
then mobilize more people
to achieve common prosperity.
So these taxes are parts of achieving the goal.
I was quite touched.
A young man under forty,
and many young entrepreneurs around
share the same mind.
For both younger and elder entrepreneurs,
their wealth comes from the society.
They also contribute back to society.
Alright, let’s see if there are more questions.
The two raised hands at the same time.
Lady first. Please.
China's GDP is growing rapidly,
and many foreigners believe that
due to the severity of the problems that China’s
economic development faces,
China’s economy should have been
in deep waters for a long time.
The reality is that not only did we not get into trouble,
but we have made great progress instead.
This is also called the "mystery of the Chinese
economy" by many Western scholars.
I would like to ask Prof. Zhang,
facing so many problems, how does China
still make such great progress?
I'd like to ask our young friend, what do you do?
I am a student.
What major are you studying?
international trade.
Very good, it is related to your study.
Please have a seat.
The mystery of the Chinese economy.
First, the West can’t understand China.
According to their logic,
China’s economy has already collapsed a million times.
Basically every two or three years,
I could hear public opinions
saying that China's economy is about to fall apart.
The most known is Zhang Jiadun.
It is quite embarrassing.
The audience laughs every time he appears in public.
His prediction on the breakdown of China's
economy was exact to the year and month.
So he mispredicted every time.
When China joined the WTO in 2001,
he said that China’s economy would
collapse in five years.
When five years passed, he said
it would be another year later.
Now it has been regarded as a joke.
The mystery behind this is that China
has formed its own set of practices.
I call it the China Path. It's very impressive.
Although the China Path is not perfect,
it can already compete with
the Western model at this level.
For example, our economic model
is a mixed economy,
which includes the central government
for strategic planning
and local government for competitive planning,
plus companies.
So the China’s economy has three engines,
while others only have two.
Actually, the concern from this friend is very common.
Indeed, we hear many negative opinions
about China’s economy.
So people are worrying about
themselves and also the country.
But in fact we have walked all the way.
We still have a lot of experience and
are dealing with many problems.
We are also paying attention to these hidden worries.
We should be confident.
This is China.
Yes, this is China. Well said.
China Now with Zhang Weiwei
Our friend over here, who raised his hand just now.
- Good evening Prof. Zhang and host.
- Welcome.
When it comes to the gap between rich and poor,
people don’t care about your income and your job.
They just ask where you live.
If you say that you live in the suburbs [of Shanghai]
like Nanhui or Hangtou,
they will think that you belong to
the middle and low-income group.
Do you live in Hangtou?
Yeah.
We are quite close.
I also live in that area. So we are neighbors.
I used to live in Huangpu District downtown.
In other words, will this reflect
the gap between rich and poor?
The so-called rich people live in the city or downtown,
while poor people can only live in remote suburbs.
- You're actually talking about ...
-Have a seat. He's talking about individual feelings.
Your question actually belongs to the cultural level.
In the past 30 to 40 years of reform and opening up,
housing conditions have been largely changed.
Years later, your choice today might be the best.
That's true.
You are a local,
so you feel strongly about this.
This was also the case a hundred years ago.
Shanghai was separated into the upper corner
and the lower corner.
One is a good location and the other is bad.
This phenomenon is called "snobbish" in English.
This is a common problem in big cities.
In fact, this mindset can totally be discarded.
The new Shanghainese don't
care about these things at all.
They will live where they like.
I live in Pudong now.
Forty years ago, no one wanted to live in Pudong.
But now Pudong is now in trend.
I’ve been to Hangtou, and I think it has
good [future] prospects.
It also has a historical town.
After the cultural resources are leveraged,
maybe it will become the next Zhouzhuang.
[a well-known canal town]
Many people will envy you living near the old town.
So I think the cultural mindset will change,
and we can really see the changes
happening step by step.
I can actually list many benefits of living in Hangtou.
The air is cleaner than the urban area.
In addition, it has better commutes,
and is convenient for grocery shopping.
The surroundings are very quiet.
No interference from downtown areas.
Just like Prof. Zhang said
the more our society develops,
the more you will feel the inadequacies
will become advantages in the future.
It is a non-stop transformation.
So I hope each of us can enjoy this
transformation in China’s development.
Enjoy the explorations in a new sense.
It will be great.
Prof. Zhang, you said that when observing China,
we should avoid being "blind men and an elephant".
In the end, I would like to ask
is there any other advice you have?
I think it is urgent to innovate the indicator system.
The West is quite good at it.
One indicator after another.
But they are all easy to crack [to find flaws in].
But they still dare to use them.
So I think from this aspect,
first, our scholars should not be bamboozled;
second, we need to establish our own indicator system,
and use it to observe the West and the whole world.
Alright, thank you Prof. Zhang.
Another round of pplause to Prof. Zhang .
China has risen in peace.
The economy has been developed,
but people are still bad-mannered.
Must it be that competition is
greater than cooperation?
The vast majority of Chinese benefit
from the reform and opening up.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 微信公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组